said welcome back, and today we are
going to cover the last topic of Kafka
stream, that is window.
So,
we all know that Kafka streams are
infinite. Like there is no start, no
end. New stream keeps on arriving. So,
there is we can say no start, no end.
So, what if our business requirement is
to answer
"How many orders we received in last 1
hour?"
Will you be able to answer from the
stream? Kafka stream, like events are
keep on coming. No,
we won't be able to answer.
Okay? The max till now what we have done
is go with the stateful processing. So,
we have a stream of events,
and we have used this count.
Group by key, count. The max we can have
is a K table, like which stores or
maintain the state in RocksDB.
We all we can have is like for this key,
how many records you have seen so far?
Okay? But,
this will not help you answer how many
orders received between, let's say, 10
to 11.
No, we cannot answer that.
So, that's where window comes into the
picture.
So, window is a time-based boundary used
to group records from an infinite stream
into finite chunks. So, consider this
with an example.
So, these are the events.
And let's say now we are grouping based
on the window. We will see what type
different types of windows there. But
now here if you see,
for each key, now we have multiple
grouping based on the time. Window
start, let's say, 10 to 11, how many
events you have seen?
Same key, but between this time, 11 to
12,
how many events you have seen?
So, now if anyone ask how many orders
received between 10 to 11, we can do a
simply look up here
key and the start and end and we can be
able to answer that. So you know that
RocksDB provide
interactive queries.
Okay?
I will not be covering interactive
queries because if we understand this
interactive queries is like just
understanding the syntax. That's all.
So it's just like which
RocksDB name
you want to query. So every state store
we can give a name.
So provide the name which you want to
query, the key
and if it is a window, then you can also
provide from and to.
So it will provide you the data. That's
all.
So the major thing is to understand the
things.
Okay?
So now let's go one level more deeper
into the windows.
So we have very three important time
concepts. Many engineers get confused in
this one.
The first is event time.
Second is record time stamp.
And the third is a stream time.
So event time is the one when the event
actually happened in the real world. So
when you have a payload
within that, let's say you have created
at. That's what actual event time is.
It's not like when Kafka you are able to
write into the Kafka or when Kafka
received, when Kafka start processing
it. No.
When actually event happened in the real
world. So within your payload order
payload, when the order was actually
created 10:01.
That's what event time is.
Record time stamp is like
the producer. So there are two way. The
producer
assign the timestamp before sending the
record
to the you can say that a broker.
Okay? So, we have a Kafka broker.
So, Kafka producer
send
this event.
Okay? So, before that it also assign the
timestamp.
So, that is also known as record
And we also have a way that
if you don't want to use the producer
assign timestamp, we can configure log
append time. When the broker assign the
timestamp when the record is appended to
the log. So, one is like producer has
published.
So, producer has assigned one timestamp.
If you don't want to use that, you want
to have like when actually the event
write into the log.
Okay? So,
that also we can use, but that is
assigned by broker.
That is assigned by broker.
So, generally these two times, this or
So, there are two types, right?
Timestamp one is
you're using default. Let's say default
is
whatever the timestamp producer is
giving us. So, that will be used.
If you don't want to use the time when
producer publish the event, and you want
it to use the time when the record is
actually appended to the log, then you
have to use you have to you can say that
add into your application.properties.
Hey,
uh we want to use log append time.
So,
it will use this time when the record is
actually appended to the log.
So, that's why I put or.
So, this is known as record timestamp.
So, that's why
record timestamp is
either
Don't get confused. either
event published
time
or
event
uh record event is appended
to log.
So, any time could be possible depending
upon what approach we are using. This is
default. And if you want this one, you
have to just add a configuration log up
and time. Then this will be used. But
this is known as record time. So, now
here if you see
this is your payload, which has the
event time actually happened.
Outside of this, outside of this
you can say that a value, or you can say
that your record
there is certain additional data data,
you can say that metadata, timestamp.
So, that
is your actual record timestamp.
And by default, during window
this time is only used. So, now
during window, we will discuss like a
start time
end time.
So, you would be discussing here what
time it is. Are we discussing event
time, record timestamp, stream time? So,
start time end time when we are saying,
by default Kafka stream make use of this
record timestamp.
Okay?
And the third is stream time. Stream
time is the highest record timestamp
observed so far. What does it mean? Now,
let's say you have an events.
Another is at 10:10. Another is at
11:00.
So, let's say multiple events are
coming. It is possible that some late
events are coming. So, even though at
11:00 you have already
record an event.
Okay, and but you also getting some late
events, which happened on 10:30.
Like this, multiple events can come.
So, a stream time is highest record
timestamp. So, it is always you can say
that, increasing. So, when this event
happen,
stream time is 10.
When 10:10,
when an any particular order
with let's say record time stamp, record
time stamp is 10:10. So, it will
increase the stream time 10:10. See, it
is increasing.
Then 11.
Any record with record time stamp 11.
So, here if you see, earlier it was
10:10, now I got 11, so it will also
increase 11.
Now, see this. Now, I received an order
with the record time stamp 10:30. It
will see that, "Hey, my stream time is
already 11. I should not go back."
So, it will not change your stream time.
Stream time is 11 only.
Now, when you get another order and its
record time stamp is 11:40, it will say
that, "Hey, my stream time is 11. Now, I
got 11:40, so it will update itself."
So, stream time is always increasing.
So, you might be thinking, "What it is?"
See,
Kafka do not works on our
like whatever the clock wall clock, you
can say that. So, currently, let's say
we have 10:30. So, it's not like Kafka
also say that, "Hey, current time is
10:30." Kafka works on
till
when
till or instead of till what time
I have
seen the records.
So, it is totally depend upon the
record. Till what time I have seen the
records? So, till 11, it has seen the
record.
So, even though some late records are
coming 10:30, it won't update itself.
Okay? Till 11, it has seen.
Got it? Stream time?
Now, one doubt might be coming at this
point of time.
I told you by default, Kafka stream
window
make use of this record time stamp. And
this record timestamp is like
two scenarios.
Like one is producer assigned the
timestamp.
Or another is this broker assigned the
timestamp when the record is appended to
the log. Okay, depend. But for this
we can say that
a timestamp which is present outside
this your actual
record.
Okay? So this is overall record. I would
say that actual your order. You for
example.
So
currently we are saying that by default
window is using
record timestamp, this timestamp.
But what if
I my business is to use this event time?
Can I change it? This default.
Yes, we can easily change that also.
So there is already one interface
provided by Kafka stream timestamp
extractor.
All we have to do is we have to
implement that. Let's say I have
implemented order timestamp extractor,
this one, and provide an implementation
for this method. Very simple method.
Let's say you have a record.
Okay? So from this record
you just read this value.
You this is your order. From this order
read this created at. That's what I have
done.
So from this record read the value. Now
this is my order. Order.getcreatedat.
It's in millisecond. So now this time
would be used.
And in the application.properties I have
just configured that which time
extractor to use. So I told that use
this order time extractor.
That's all. So it is possible that we
can control
which
timestamp
event time or record timestamp
which to use
during window.
Okay, you You use a stream time. It's
just like between even time or record
time is there. So, if you
don't do this if you don't do this
by default it will use this
record time is there like whatever it is
coming here.
Outside of your value.
Got it? So, this three time is clear and
also
this is stream time is very important. I
will tell you how, but
at this point of time
keep this all three
in mind. Okay?
So, we have different types of windows.
So, I will just cover three important
types of windows which basically cover
all type of reportings which we have to
do.
One is tumbling. Another is hopping. The
third is session windows.
There could be more, but
I believe that these three covers most
of the report reportings which we
require.
Let's first understand tumbling windows.
Tumbling windows are fixed size
and each record belongs to exactly one
window.
Let's say that our window size is 10
minute.
So, what Kafka stream has is
logically Okay, so
it like
10 0 0 10. So, see 10 10 difference
window it created.
0 0 to 10, 10 to 20, 20 to 30 like this.
Now, let's say any record comes at
10:07.
So, which window it will belongs to?
It will belongs to this one.
Okay? Exactly one window.
So, below is the example of how data is
actually stored in K table. That's again
it's my understanding.
So, here if you see
now our K table
is not simply just key. It's like key,
window start, window end.
And let's say the value is like whatever
the aggregate you are using, let's say
count or something.
So, for each key
you can have different
windows. Then, let's say I have, let's
say, 5 minutes
window. In the tumbling window, I have a
window size of 5 minutes.
So, for this key, 10 to 10:05, 10:05 to
10:10, 10:10 to 10:15. Like this, you
can have
different windows. And like whatever the
count in this one. Similarly, for key
two also, you can have.
One generally misconception is that like
we have all the windows present even if
there is no data,
no record itself.
So, let's say
we have the key
key-1 which arrives at this two time.
So,
how this data would be stored? Let's say
key one.
Now, the time window is 5 minutes.
Okay? So, 10.
So, it would be, you know that, 10 to
10:05. So, 10:02 falls into this.
Okay? So, 10 to 10:05, one.
Then, 10:13. So, 10:13 is within the
range
10 to 10:15.
So, 10:10 to 10:15 for this key is one.
Okay? So, each record
falls within one window. And now, here
if you see that there is no record at,
let's say, 10:05
to 10:10. There is no record, so there
is no entry also.
So, whenever there is a record, if entry
if window is required, then only you
will see. Unnecessary, it won't create
all the windows
Entry. Let's say with zero.
Okay? And also one important thing is
that window start time is inclusive and
window end is exclusive. So, it's like
this.
So, you generally use case where we
tumbling we can use is
order per 5 minutes, revenue per hour,
API request per minute.
Then in those scenario, we can go with
this tumbling.
Now,
very important that
this two scenarios, if you understand
that we would be able to answer most of
the questions.
One is
this doubt itself. This doubt like does
window remains open or not? Now, before
I just read this out, let's first
understand
the grace period.
All the situation without grace period
and with grace period.
So, this definition is clear, right?
With this one. If it is not clear,
things will get more clear with this
one.
Let's say without grace period.
What's the scenario?
So,
just assume that we are saying that
windows are getting created.
Now, the one question comes into my mind
is this windows remain open?
Let's say currently it's 10:10.
Now, let's say after
2 hours, 12.
Does this window remain open?
Now, let's say after 2 hours, if any
event comes for let's say 10
for 13.
Will this again get updated?
Is this open window still open? It can
like always be updated?
So, answer lies with the grace period.
So, in the without grace period,
as soon as window is closed,
as soon as
you can say that window end time is
crossed.
And how you know that window end time is
crossed is based on extreme time.
Let's see with an example. You will
understand more clear.
>> [snorts]
>> Let's say window size is 5 minutes.
And this is the
extreme of events, for example.
The first record is coming at 10:31. All
belongs to the same key, let's say. Same
key is, let's say, order one.
All belongs to the same key.
The first event comes at 10:31, second
10:32, third 10:41, and another
there is one 10:33, some late event is
coming.
Now, let's say what's the behavior.
>> [snorts]
>> So, first,
a record at 10:31 is coming.
Okay. So, I told you about the extreme
time. Extreme time is like till what
time
the
record has been observed.
So, since this is the first extreme
time, it will update to 10:31 also.
Okay?
So, current time window open
is because window size is 5 minutes, and
10:31 is coming, so the window is 10:32
to 10:35. So, these are you can say that
logically 00 05 5 to 10 10 to 15,
likewise. So, it knows that
key is order one,
window is start inclusive 10:30
10:35 window end, the count is one.
Okay? So, this record is accepted.
Simple.
Second. Now, the record at 10:32 is
coming.
Stream time
become 10:32.
Okay, the same.
So, current time window, it will also
fall within this only, 10:30 to 10:35.
So, it will just update the count, so it
become two.
This is also handled properly.
Now, 10:41. See this.
So, 10:41 record is coming 10:41. What
would be the stream time?
It would become 10:41.
Okay. Now, here if you see
the current window for the 10:41 would
be 10:40 to 10:45. So, this
record at this should fall into this
range, this window.
Okay. So, currently this window is not
present, so it will create 10:40 to
10:45. It will create one.
Also, notice that the previous window it
is now closed. How it knows that? See, a
stream time, the current time is now
greater than your window end time.
Okay, means
the time is crossed.
So, your window is closed.
Got it? Because our 10:41 stream time
stream time, that's where it is
important. A stream time is now greater
than your end window end time.
So, if that is true
your window is closed.
Currently this is open. Why? Because
window end time is currently
you can say that a stream time has not
crossed this window end time. So, that's
why it is open. So, it is open for
updates.
Now,
10:33 event is coming.
So, what is the stream time currently?
10:41. So, will it get updated? No, it
won't get again to 10:33. A stream time
always proceed forward forward.
So, 10:33 falls into which range? It
falls into 10
uh 30 to 10
35.
So, it falls into 10:30 to 10:35.
But, will it be able to update it? No.
This window is already closed.
Okay, this window is already closed. So,
this would be discarded.
Right? That's what we have seen here,
but with this uh example. Now, let's say
with grace period.
So, grace period is like
window is not closed suddenly. When it
is closed? When a stream
time
is greater than window
end time. This is what we have seen.
Plus grace.
Plus grace time also. Now, the formula
become instead of this
now formula become this.
Plus grace time also. So, grace time is
only useful is while deciding the
closing. Can the window be closed or
not?
Okay, without grace time
this is the only formula. But, after
grace with grace
the grace time is also added to your
window end time and then it is decided.
So, see this example. Again, the same
example. So, here if you see
the first is simple. 10:31
recorded at 10:31, the stream 10:31
added.
10:32
simple.
10:32 stream is 10:32
again fall into the same window. So, it
got updated.
So, here but at this point of 10 can you
tell what is what So, till when this
window will be open? Open till
window end time is 10:35
plus what is the grace? 10 minutes.
>> [snorts]
>> So, this will be open till
10:45.
Okay?
>> [snorts]
>> So, third.
Record at 10:41.
Stream time 10:41. So, its window is
10:42 10:45. So, it will have this.
But, will it close any window? No.
So, the previous window is also open
because end is 10:35.
Stream is 10:41. It's crossed already.
But, now it is not closed because
grace period is added. 10:35 plus 10.
So, 10:45. Till 10:45, it would be open.
So, till it is not closed.
Now, you are receiving at 10:33. So,
which window it belongs to?
10:30 to 10:35.
Is it is still open? Yes, till 10:45 it
is open. So, it will update to three.
Got it? Understood the
concept of grace
time and also the usage of stream time.
Why it is very important.
>> [snorts]
>> It helps in deciding when the window can
be closed.
Clear?
The tumbling window is clear, right?
The second is
Uh yeah, before that uh just see the
method definition.
So, see this with this example.
So, till now we have already seen that
like once you have an order
order dot let's say select key like
how you want it to
like if you want to change the key
then you do group by key. We have
already seen that.
Now, we can also tell like how you want
to group. Like you want to group
windowed by.
Windowed by
time windows dot of size and grace.
So, there are two flavor.
One is without grace, another is with
grace.
Of size and grace, off-size with no
When you use this method, you only
provide
the size, window size. When you use this
window size plus the grace period.
So, this is window size is 5 minutes,
the grace is 1 minute.
>> [snorts]
>> Rest everything is same, dot count.
All we have just provided like I want
this window.
>> [snorts]
>> Clear?
So, but if you are using like this
flavor, you can also have like if you
remember during materialized
we are using earlier key value store.
But that is you can say that by default.
And again, you don't
have to write it. This is again an
optional. You can just simply do
materialized as.
Since we have already provided this in
the metadata, it will automatically know
it has to use window store. So, but here
if you see
instead of key value now in the RocksDB
over state store, earlier it was only
key value.
But now we are specifically saying that
it's a window store.
It's not now key value, it's a window.
But again, we don't have to write this
since we have already provided windowed
by it will be added in the metadata.
And when you do ultimately the count, it
knows
what type of state store it has to
create.
Only one thing you have to notice the
return type. Earlier it was key table.
Your key value. So, let's say string
comma string. Now it is windowed string.
So, it's not normal. So, this is
actually your key, key type.
So, my key is still a string only. But
it is of windowed string.
So, windowed So, this object if you see,
you will have a key.
Whatever the type it is coming. Let's
say K.
Okay?
Whatever the type it is coming, so I'm
sending the string. So, it would be a
string.
Key.
Then it will also have duration. Start
time, duration, end time.
Got it? So, now you can say that just a
wrapper. So, apart from key
start and end.
So, that's why I told you
this is how actually
it is record into the RocksDB. Key,
start, and end.
>> [snorts]
>> So, this is you can see that one.
So, we can start it. Let's see.
Let's start the producer. So, we have
already have the setup.
That is we have all done it multiple
times.
So, producer is a started.
Now, here the same thing.
So, this is our stream.
This is the K table.
Now, here if you see windowed by
off size and grace I am using.
So, window size is 5 minutes. And here
if you see, this is the grace.
Now, here if you see return by windowed,
so here if you see, whatever you are
passing, that would become your key
type.
So, my key is still a string. But now it
is wrapped inside this.
And rest is window.
Start millisecond, end millisecond.
Okay?
So, once you done this
Now, after that you can have output.
Like So, you can put the data into
the output topic. So, currently I'm also
printing it here. Peek. I'm doing
peeking here and I'm just putting
system.out.print ln. You don't have to
do this.
Okay?
But,
just for like in here console also we
get printed like what's the key, start
time, end time, and the count. I'm just
printing it here also.
But, all we have is like we can publish
it to output topic.
And here if you see produced with
like key serializer or you can say that
value serializer.
So, value is our long. So, that
serializer.
And here if you see that key serializer.
So,
So, here if you see that uh we don't
have just normal string. Key is not a
normal string. It is windowed the
string.
Okay? So, that's why it has a specific
serializer for it one. Window serializer
deserializer.
Time window starts from a string. So,
internally it will decide like how it
wanted uh like window
size is 10.
And it just record the start time.
10 0 0. It will automatically compute
the end time. So, how it wanted to
showcase this information.
Because our key is now not just a
string. It has uh key plus window start
plus window end.
Okay? So, that's why it's own serializer
for the key.
So, data, whatever we are getting,
it would be published to the output
topic. And from this output topic you
can compute the reports.
So, let's run this also.
Let's start this.
Okay?
So, this is clear, right? Till now. Now,
we will hit it. But, this is clear,
right?
Everything is same. All the difference
is that
we are just telling what type of window
we want to use.
So, currently we are using tumbling
window.
Okay? And we are just printing it here
dot peak. So, that is not necessary.
All we have to do is like publishing it
to the topic.
So, now we can hit it.
Let's say one time.
And another time. Two times we have hit.
So, count should be two for that
particular range.
So, first let's see output output topic
has got this record or not.
So, the same.
Ordered count topic partition zero. So,
that's the name.
What's the name of the ordered count
topic?
>> [snorts]
>> So, it has not seen. Let's say into
broker one logs. So, we have two
brokers, right? So, let's it's log also.
Yeah. So, in broker one it has gone.
So, here if you see, so currently it's
in serializer form, that's why we are
not able to see.
But, here if you see key is there.
O hyphen one. So, key is present.
And the rest time
that is like serialized form, that's why
we are not able to see, but yeah, some
record has gone into this output topic.
But, we are also printing into our
console, so this might have also come
here.
So, key is this.
Is start
is
0500.
So, 5 minutes we have given the range,
right? With window is what we have
given.
Window size we have given 5 minutes.
So, 5:05. So, this is a start window,
this is end window, count is two because
two times we have hit.
You got it?
So, the same thing
is the same thing has gone into this
output topic. From this output topic
you can say that the reports
whichever is required that can be
generated.
Clear?
The second is hopping window.
>> [snorts]
>> Now, hopping window is also fixed size.
And it advanced by fixed interval.
Because of this, each record may belongs
to multiple windows. Now, let's see.
Let's say window size again is 10
minutes, but advanced by 5 minutes.
So, now here if you see
window one is 10 to 10:10. 10 minutes
size.
But advanced by 5 minutes. So, next it
it will create 10:05 to 10:15.
10:10
to 10:20.
So, now here if you see
start time from start time it advanced
by this many minutes.
So, now let's say any record comes at
10:07, it belongs to multiple windows.
In 10 to 10:10, yes, it belongs to
window one.
10:05 to 10:15, it also belongs to this
window. So, one record can belongs to
multiple windows.
So, sometime we have a use case that
order in last 1 hour, but update me
every let's say 2 minutes, 5 minutes,
every 6 minutes.
So, in that scenarios
you want this hopping window.
Because you want every update, let's say
1 hour, whatever the window size, let's
say I need
10 minutes.
How many orders have been done?
10 of the 10 minutes size, but give me
after every 5 minutes. So, you can use
this.
>> [snorts]
>> Again, let's see the same flow without
grace and with grace.
I've
I want that you can pause the video
here.
If you understand this
without grace, with grace, just see this
and try to
evaluate yourself what would be the
output.
So,
let's say these are the event. What is
the virtual, you can say that visualize
the windows it would create as let's say
window size is 10 minute, advanced by 5
minutes. So, 10 20
27 it is coming, right? 20 to 30, that
would be one window.
Then, advanced by 5 minutes. 25 to 35.
Then, 30
to 40. Then, from 35 to 45. 40 to 50.
Like this,
generally videos
uh windows have been created.
Now, let's see first.
This record is coming at 10:27.
Very similar, stream time would be
10:27.
So,
current active window at this point of
time.
So, here if you see,
10:20 to 10:30.
Yes, it can go.
5 minutes move. Uh your advance is,
let's say, 5 minutes. So, it then also
goes to 10:25 to 10:35 also. This will
get updated.
Okay? Because see, virtually,
just I'm if you think
this uh
windows would be look like this. 20 to
30. Then, 5 minutes advance, 25 to 35.
So, here if you see,
10:27 would lie here and would lie here.
Okay, that's why these two are updated.
Now second, order at 10:28.
Again, falls into here and falls into
here.
Okay, so both get updated.
Here it is.
Third, now let's say the event arrives
at 10:41.
So,
what would be the stream time?
It will increase to 10:41.
Correct. So, 10:41 belongs to which
window?
One window is 10:35 to 45.
Another is 10:40 to 50.
Okay, 10 minutes gap.
And advanced by 5 minutes. So, these two
windows.
So, first of all, these two windows
already exist? Currently no, so it will
create new.
So, it will create new.
So, this will get updated one. This also
get updated one.
Now, what happened to the previous
window?
That should also close, right? Because
let's say stream time is 10:41. So, it
will see that stream time greater than
window end time. If that is true, close
those windows.
So, 10:30.
Already
back than the stream time, so this would
be closed.
10:35, already back.
Okay, this is now past.
Stream time is 10:41. So, that is also
closed. These two would be open because
the stream time is 10:41. This is
end is 45, end is 50.
So, these two will be remain open.
Now, the record comes at 10:29.
So, this is late event, so stream time
will not update itself. So, it has
already seen record till 10:41.
Now, the 10:29 belongs to what all?
You can say that windows. So, one it
belongs to 20 to 30 and 25 to 35.
Both are present, 20 to 30, 25 to 35.
Will it update? No, both are closed.
So, it would be discarded.
The same you can do with the grace
itself.
Now, apart from window size and hop, we
have a grace 10 minutes.
So,
first
two are very simple. The same thing.
10:27.
So, this window and this window is
updated.
10:28.
Both lies into the same window, so they
are These values are updated.
Now, 10:41.
So, 10:41 belongs to this
two groups.
So, these are updated. But, now notice
that when we have to close,
so this window when
it will open. Till till what time it
should be open? So, window end time
plus grace 10. So, till 10:40 it should
remain open.
And this one, 10:35
plus 10. Till 10:45 it should remain
open.
So, current stream time is
current stream time is 10:41. So, that
is greater than 10:40, so this will be
closed.
And this is still 10:45, so this will
remain open.
Now, at 10:29 a record is coming. Your
stream time will not update.
Okay. So, 10:29 belongs to this two
windows. 20 to 30, 25 to 35. 20 to 30 is
already closed, it will not update.
25 to 35.
This is still open till 10:45. Stream
time is already 10:41. So, it will
update. So, this will get update.
So, your record is kind of accepted.
Clear?
>> [snorts]
>> Method is almost similar. The same off
size with no grace, off size and grace.
Only thing is like uh your window size
After that you just provide dot advanced
by how how much you want to advance.
That's all. And with grace, your window
size
then your grace
and advanced by dot advanced by how much
which you want
Sorry, how much by what time you want to
advance.
The same thing.
Nothing difference.
Clear, right?
>> [snorts]
>> Now the last one I have wanted to cover
is session windows. This is sometime
useful. Let's say you have to find out
like, okay, a particular user comes.
Then how many time like what's the
average user session?
Let's say I have a website. I want to
know like for each user what's the
average
average user
session like 5 minutes it is stay, 10
minutes it stay or 2 minutes it stay or
2 minutes it stay.
So session window.
So it group events that occur close
together in time.
Now at this point of time, we have to
think in a different manner. Now think
from the record perceptive, not from the
time perceptive. Now there is no fixed
size window. Let's say
10 minutes. No.
Now it is based on record.
Okay, there is no fixed window size.
It's now we have like group all the
events that occur close together.
So your window can keep on increasing if
events keep on happening close together.
But when the window will close? That's
where we have a period of inactivity.
Let's say
till here
till now window is there till 10:10.
And we have provided that inactivity
period is let's say 5 minutes. If 5
minutes there is no activity,
then we can consider that this window is
closed. So, till 10:10. Now, let's say
at 10:12, a record is come.
Yes, window increase.
10:12.
Now, but let's say at event come now at
10:30.
Will 10:30 part of the same window? No,
here if you see 30 and 12, now it's
inactivity period is more than 5
minutes, let's say.
So, this window this session is closed
and it will create new session start
from 10:30 now.
So, that's the idea. Now, you are
totally rely on records occurrence, not
the time. And there is no fixed window
size.
Understand this.
Now, we have to define inactivity gap.
What's the inactivity gap? Again,
without grace, with grace, understand
that.
Very simple, like it's again very
simple. Inactivity gap is this. This is
the occurrence of the events.
Now, first.
10:27.
Okay. What would be the stream time?
So, since this is the first record, you
can say that your session is started.
So, you have only one.
10:27, 10:27. I told you we don't have
fixed window.
Okay.
So, at this point of time we have only
one record with the start and end same.
Record is count is one.
Now, another event happened at 10:29.
What is the stream time? 10:29, okay.
Now, understand the difference.
So, 10:29 and 10:27,
only 2 minutes difference.
And we have an inactivity gap of 5
minutes. So, this is like very nearby.
Okay. So, it belongs to the same
session. So, now my end time
becomes
10:29.
And count increase to two.
Now here the third
10:41
Stream time 10:41 What's the difference?
10:41 minus 10:29 12 minutes. So now
here if you see this 12 minute is more
than our inactivity.
So it's a new session.
So 10:41 to 41 one. It's a new session.
But what about the old session? Will it
close? The formula is same.
Stream time greater than window end
time.
So stream time is 10:41. Window end time
is 10:29.
Closed.
Okay?
Now
at 10:32 event arrive. What is the
stream time? 10:41.
Okay. So this 10:32 belongs to which you
can say that a session. So 10:32 if you
see 10:29
only 3 minutes gap. It can belongs to
the same session. But this session is
already closed. You can't update it.
Okay? And it cannot uh 10:32 and 10:41
What's the difference?
Okay. Start is 10:41.
So here if you see
9 minutes gap. So 32 and 41
9 minutes more than 5 minutes, right? So
it can't be part of this session also.
So ultimately this is discarded.
Okay?
With grace
inactivity and grace is 14 minutes.
Now let's see how it would be happen.
First is simple 10:27
10:29 again very simple.
The same part what we have seen. Now
here till 10:41.
Now 10:41
So the difference is 12 minutes.
It can't be part of
the same session which we already have.
So that's why it's it will create a new
session.
So, the same thing.
But, the previous session will it be
closed?
So, now stream time
greater than
window end time
plus grace.
Window end time is 10:29.
Grace is 14 minutes we have returned.
So, it will be open till 10:43. Stream
time is 10:41. So, it will not close at
this point of time. So, it is still
open.
Now, order comes at 10:32.
Okay?
So, first of all, it will find out all
from this all give me all the records
with are within
plus minus let's say 14 minutes. That's
our
uh inactivity. Inactivity is 5 minutes,
right? Plus minus let's say 5 minutes,
which can
which you can say that we have to find
the probability like what all records it
can update.
Okay? So, first we have found this.
10:32, right? So, let's find this 10:29.
Can it be part of this?
32 minus 10:29
3 minutes gap.
So, it can be part of this same session
because
the gap is only 3 minutes and we have
inactivity defined 5 minutes. So, yes.
It is uh possible to update it. So, now
one thing I have done is So, now window
is increased. 10:32. Count is increased
three.
And also here if you see, the closing
time will also get increased.
So, 10:32
plus grace time.
So, it would be now 10:46 is the closing
time now.
Okay? Now, second it will see.
Can it be part of this session also? 32.
Here if you see.
So, 10:32 and 10:41.
What's the gap? So, totally 9 minutes
gap, which is greater than 5 minutes.
So, it can't be part of this session
now.
Okay? So, only it update this.
Now, one interesting part, let's say.
When this also is within 5 minutes,
second one, what would happen?
So, interesting use case of merging
session. The same thing, only a
difference I have done is instead of
10:41, I changed it to 10:36.
So, this is same, this is same.
Now, 10:36 again,
here if you see what would be from
there, let's see that.
So, record comes at 10:36, a stream
10:36.
What is the difference?
36 29 is 6 7 minutes,
which is
you can say that more than our
inactivity period 5 minutes. So, it will
create a new session.
So, we have created a new session.
Is previous window closed? No, it would
be open till
10:43 because of the grace.
Till now, everything same what we have
seen previously.
Now, the interesting, 10:32 late is
coming.
So, 10:32 is stream time is 10:36.
The first, it will check 10:29 and 32,
what's the gap? 3 minutes gap, which is
less than 5 minutes. So, can it be part
of this session? Yes.
So, 10:27 to 10:32, it can become.
Okay?
Also, it will check with this, 10:36.
So, 10:32
and the second event is started at
10:36.
What's the time gap?
Only 4 minutes.
So, means this 10:32 becomes a bridge
between this. So, ultimately it's become
10:27 to 10:36, one session.
So, earlier there were two different
session,
but this 10:32 becomes a bridge now.
Okay? so ultimately this become one
session.
Got it?
So, 10:32 to 10:29
3 minutes gap, which is less than
inactivity.
So, 10:32 record
can be part of this session.
And it also let 10:36
the new the second event
session started at 10:36 and 10:32
gap is 4 minutes.
So, again less than 5 minutes. So, it
belongs to the second session also.
So, that's why
it merged the session. 10:27 to 10:36 it
become one and it will update the count
and it will update the closing time
also.
Okay, so this this like understand from
the record perceptor.
Not from the time. There is no fixed
window.
Okay, it's just like
records keep on coming
within a particular till inactivity
period is not over.
Window will keep on increasing. That's
all.
Okay.
Use case I have already told you that
sometime we have to find how long user
browse.
So, that we can compute average session
duration you wanted to send. Find out.
Um method definition is this.
Session windows dot
of inactivity gap with no grace
of inactivity gap and grace.
So, the same thing mostly windowed by
session window
of inactivity gap and grace.
This is your
inactivity period and this is your grace
time.
That's all.
Okay.
So, we have already seen the
implementation wise also. Very similar.
If you understand this implementation is
very similar.
Okay, now once the record are once this
data is pushed into your output topic
the reports can be generated out of it.
Okay, so but the only thing is you have
to decide for which use case which
window you have to use.
Usage is very similar. Usage is very
simple.
Earlier in the state the stateful
processing we have seen this this this.
And also we have seen count. All we have
to do is like
define which window to use. That's all.
And only difference is like now it is
not simple key,
it's windowed
key type. Your key is now wrapped.
Key
window start time window end time.
If you think from that perspective in
the mind itself
everything is clear.
Okay, with this our stream is completed
till windows also.
Any doubt let me know in the comment
section we can discuss further. Bye.